Boker tov, today's דף daf is קנ"ו, kuf nun vav, the penultimate
דף. daf.
We start with bottom of קנ"ה עמוד ב' kuf nun hay amud
bet and we are talking about various things related to feeding farm
animals. So we dealt with the issues about טירחא tircha and turning
something into food and force-feeding your animals. Anyway, now we get to
an issue that is finally turning on something related to a דאורייתא
de-oraita about mixing the water with the bran and is that a
concern about לישה lisha about kneading? I actually think by the way
yesterday just to show how little I know about farm, I translated
words consistently yesterday as זואט zvatt when it was really שחת shachat
which was really just normal hay. Anyway, I'm sure that completely confused
all of you. All right,
anyway.
We really need more Jews in agriculture.
I know, I know. All right, anyway, let's take a look. Six
lines from the bottom, two dots. מחלטין לתרנגולים. Mahaltin l'tarnigolim. So it's
getting to the line in the משנה mishna that says you can
put water into the bran but you can't knead it with a
K. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אמרית קמיה דמר, amrit kammai d'mar, I
said in front of the master, which is רבה, Rabba, מתניתין מני,
Matnitin mani,
who is our משנה mishna going like? ואמר לי רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה, V'amar li Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda because the question is why can you even
add water? Isn't the adding of the water to the bran be
like adding water to flour? Isn't that essentially also a type of
a kneading? It's at least making flour, not the act of kneading,
but this becomes the question: is that considered a form of לישה?
lisha? So he said it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda, דתניא d'tanya we taught ברייתא, beraisa, אחד נותן את הקמח ואחד
נותן לתוכו מים, echad noten et hakemach v'echad noten l'tocho mayim,
one person placed down flour, the other person poured water into it.
האחרון חייב, Ha'acharon chayav, דברי רבי, dibrei Rabbi, רבי Rabbi says that's
לישה, lisha, that's biblical לישה, lisha, adding the water to the flour.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אינו חייב עד שיגבל. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda omer eino chayav ad sheyigabel. Nope, I'm sorry, just adding the
water doesn't do it, you have to actually knead it. So our
משנה mishna allows adding water to bran, so the only way presumably
the only position it could be is רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara says to respond, דילמא עד
כאן, dilma ad kan, one minute,
maybe not. דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה התם,
Dilma ad kan lo kama Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda hatam, maybe רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda there says you don't it's
not a problem until you knead it, אלא קמח ela kemach דבר
גיבול הוא, d'bar gibul hu,
that's only by flour which is of the nature of being kneaded.
אבל מורסן דלאו בר גיבול הוא, Aval mursan d'lav bar gibul hu,
but bran
that is not a something that is subject to גיבול, gibul, which
is very strange what that means, I'll unpack that possibly in a
minute. Anyway, אפילו רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מודה, afilu Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda modeh, maybe even רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
would agree that that's a problem. Now of course you could right,
so first of all let's say one or two words about this.
What does it mean that bran is not בר גיבול? bar gibul?
The best I can understand is that it means that when you
add the water to it, it does not dissolve as readily in
the water as flour does. Is that true? Anybody know about that?
Bran? True. It is true? You add the water, it does not
dissolve right away, it doesn't turn into a dough. Right. You have
to work it more to turn it into a dough, knead it
and cook it. And then cook it. So okay, so Michael says,
you know, then actually doesn't the opposite make sense? Then you would
say that if that type of a thing then all the more
reason why bran you should say the opposite even the חכמים Chachamim
should agree by bran. Right, so this comes up in an earlier
גמרא Gemara that there are some גמרות Gemaras and תוספות Tosafot discusses
it, the other ראשונים Rishonim discuss it, some גמרות Gemaras that sound
like if it's less of a בר גיבול bar gibul of course
you have to knead it,
because only then you're doing something substantive. And some suggest like this
גמרא Gemara which is quite paradoxical that if it's not a בר
גיבול, bar gibul, it's sort of like, well, then we can't really,
it's never really going to be fully kneaded anyway. So even a
lower threshold counts as something significant, which I know is completely counterintuitive.
But it's like, well, if you're not really going to get to
a full stage of classic dough anyway, then it's already considered a
problematic even when it's at an earlier stage. Okay, it's more like
this is just all the way the best you can expect from
this mostly is some type of a loose mixture. It's a very
strange idea. Anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara suggests and the funny
thing would be then our משנה mishna would have nobody to go
like. It wouldn't even be רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara rejects it. גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא
דעתך, lo salka daiteich, it doesn't make sense. דתניא D'tanya we taught
ברייתא beraisa בהדיא, behedya, אין נותנין מים למורסן דברי רבי, ein notnin
mayim l'mursan dibrei Rabbi,
רבי Rabbi says you cannot add the water to the bran. ורבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר נותנין מים למורסן, V'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer
notnin mayim l'mursan, you can. Okay, so it does this בר גיבול
bar gibul doesn't make a difference, certainly not in that direction. And
according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda it's not
considered kneading until you actually knead it. There's a whole debate about
how we פסקן pasken about that. In general we don't even add
the water
to things that would like dissolve and so on, turn it into
a dough, not dissolve like instant tea or whatever, but oatmeal or
something that even the water is a problem
and we only under some circumstances where it might be allowed it's
only allowed with a שינוי shinui which is actually what the גמרא
Gemara is going to turn to. תנו רבנן Tano rabbanan אין גובלין
את הקלי ein govlin et hakelli ויש אומרים גובלין. v'yesh omrim govlin.
You cannot knead the קלי kelli which קלי... kelli... is like a
type of a רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says like a
wheat that's been roasted in the oven. הקלי והכרמל *hakali vehakarmel*. There
you go, right, and it makes it type of a sweet, you
know, it becomes a sweeter type of a, of a flour. So,
fine, so you cannot mix it.
Now what you'd use to make it out of is you would
make from it something called שסיסא *shasisa*, which is oil and water
and, and salt and this type of a thing and it would
be some type of like a sweet, doughy thing or something. So
anyway, you cannot do that. ויש אומרים גובלין *veyeish omrim govlin*, some
say you can. Now of course that's bizarre because that's actual kneading
it. Why should kneading it be allowed? That's like, isn't that really
לישה lisha *lisha*? So מן יש אומרים *man yeish omrim*, who are
the יש אומרים *yeish omrim*? אמר רב Rav. חסדא רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Yehuda היא *Amar Rav Chisda: Rabi Yosei berabi
Yehuda hi*. It's Rabbi Yosei ben Rabbi Yehuda who says that you
could add the water. Now, okay, but still how do you knead
it? So meaning the point is it can't be רבי Rebbe *Rebbe*,
according to רבי Rebbe. *Rebbe* as soon as you add the water
you got a problem. But according to Rabbi Yosei berabi Yehuda, the
only problem is the kneading, so the adding of the water was
okay. How about the kneading? Ah, there we have a way to
deal with that. והני מילי *vahani mili* so it immediately qualifies it,
so it's not straight allowed, it's only allowed הוא דמשני *huda meshani*.
If you do it with a שינוי shinuy. *shinuy*. So, well, it's
right, so it's very strange, you know, there are some, most of
the מלאכות *melakhos* we do, right, you know, it's אסור assur. *assur*
even if you've got a double שינוי shinuy *shinuy* and even if
it's a דרבנן *d'rabbanan* version of it and da da da da
da, right? We always have these safeguards and safeguards of safeguards. And
then every now and then you get a מלאכה *melacha* that even
if it's דאורייתא d'oraisa *d'oraysa*, חז״ל *Chazal* allowed it with a שינוי
shinuy *shinuy*. It's quite bizarre, I really can't explain it. I'll give
you another example, טוחן *tochen*, grinding. If you actually grind spices, like
you take a peppercorn and you actually grind it but you grind
it in a way that both the grinder and the vessel being
ground in are a שינוי shinuy *shinuy*, like instead of a mortar
and pestle or now we have those pepper grinders, if you take,
right, if you take let's say I don't know a cup, right,
you know, and you put it on, you know, and you put
it on a plate and you bang it like that, so because
it's not the normal thing you bang with and not the normal
thing you crush pepper on, that's actually מותר mutar, *muttar*. מותר mutar,
*muttar*? Yeah! Even דאורייתא מלאכה *d'oraysa melacha*!
I wouldn't advise it! But all I'm telling you is that's how
it's פסקן *paskened* in שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*. So there are some
things which are a שינוי shinui. *shinuy* of a מלאכה דאורייתא *melacha
d'oraysa* that for some reason חז״ל *Chazal* allowed. And here is this
case about doing טחינה *techina* as long as you do it with
a, doing לישה lisha *lisha* as long as you do it with
a שינוי shinui? *shinuy*. Now the general פסק psak. *psak* by the
way is like a double שינוי shinui. *shinuy*. I'll just go straight
to the הלכה *halacha*, which is both a שינוי shinui *shinuy* in
the way you add the water, because here we're working within רבי
Rebbe. יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yosei berabi Yehuda* who doesn't care about
adding the water, but you do a שינוי shinui *shinuy* the way
you add the water. Now how do you do a שינוי shinui
*shinuy* the way you add the water? I'm sort of, this is
going to come up in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in a minute,
but I'll just tell you sort of what the הלכה *halacha* is,
is that you reverse the normal order of things. If normally you
add the water to the flour, then you add the flour to
the water or the water to the oatmeal, so then first you
put in the water and then you put in the oatmeal let's
say. So you reverse the order and then the way you mix
it is with a שינוי shinui? *shinuy* which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is about to say. Now even when you have both of those,
I mean again the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sounds like maybe you know
this is because there's a little pushback to the idea that you
can do a מלאכה דאורייתא *melacha d'oraysa* with a שינוי shinui, *shinuy*.
So a) we say a double שינוי shinui *shinuy* because each step
could be לישה lisha. *lisha* so you need a שינוי shinui. *shinuy*
at each step. And b) we're going to see in a minute
that it's, that as a general rule we only allow it when
it's called something which is בלילה רכה belila raka, *belila raka*. בלילה
רכה belila raka, *belila raka* is like cake batter as opposed to
something which is בלילה עבה belila ava, *belila ava* which is like
dough. Okay, so once it's already cake batter consistency, it's not considered
לישה lisha. דאורייתא *lisha d'oraysa*. לישה דאורייתא *lisha d'oraysa* is only when
it has like the thickness of dough. So with those various criteria,
right, we allow it. Now there are times actually because based on
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is that even with בלילה עבה *belila ava* and there are so
if you really there are times where we would allow that even
with a בלילה עבה *belila ava*. So anyway, but it's quite amazing
that we allow these things and that, I'm giving you like the
end which incorporates the pushback from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it doesn't
even seem you need all that much. Is it the שינוי shinui.
*shinuy* of what you add? Let's say normally you add water, so
you're going to add apple juice?
No, it seems like the general approach is it has to be
the specific ways in which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames what שינויים
*shinuyim* are allowed. So let's take a look. והני מילי הוא דמשני
Vehani mili hu dameshany. *vahani mili huda meshani*. That's only if you
do it with a שינוי shinui, *shinuy*. היכי משני Heichi meshany? *heichi
meshani*? How, how do you do a שינוי shinui, *shinuy*? אמר רב
Rav חסדא על יד על יד *Amar Rav Chisda: Alyad alyad*. You
do like little by little. So that's amazing, like even just doing
a little bit at a time, I mean my God, you're doing
the actual מלאכה *melacha*, like nobody could say you could do a
מלאכה *melacha* on פחות מכשיור *pachos mikeshiur*, you know, but somehow that
is enough to define it as a שינוי shinui *shinuy*. Now again,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will add more שינויים *shinuyim* in a minute.
ושוים שבוחשין את השסיס בשבת *veshovim shebokhshin es hashsis bashabbos*. They agree
that you can sort of stir, you know, the השסיס *hashsis* on
שבת Shabbat! *Shabbos*, which is this mixture with, you know, honey and
all this stuff of this flour.
Which is funny, didn't we just say that you needed to do
a שינוי shinui. *shinuy*? So we'll see about that in a minute.
So let's take a look.
One minute. ושותין זיתום המצרי *veshosin zeisum hamitzri*. And they also agree
that you can drink this זיתום המצרי *zeisum hamitzri*, this type of
an Egyptian, what do they call it, have, is it a vinegar
type of a thing? I forget. Anyway, beer? What? Beer? Alright, whatever
it is, anyway, this type of a thing which would sometimes be
drunk for רפואה *refuah* purposes but because other people drink it... for
normal purposes, it's not a רפואה problem, so completely unrelated. So anyway,
now the גמרא Gemara focuses in on the idea that you can
stir this שתית. shatit. והאמרת אין גובלין. Veha'amarta ein govlin. One minute,
you're not allowed to knead! How is how are you allowed to
do this? לא קשיא הא בעבא והא ברכיכא. Lo kashya ha be'ava
ha berakika.
So it's a difference between whether again I told you whether it's
a thick mixture like dough or a thin one like cake batter.
So and okay, but even a thin presumably that's not מותר לכתחילה.
mutar lechatchila. So then it adds yet another qualification. והני מילי הוא
דמשני. So although it said like oh, you can stir it no
problem, the גמרא Gemara immediately pushes back and adds two qualifications. This
שתית, shatit, this type of a honey wheat mixture whatever, you can
only do if number
one it's a loose mixture and number two if it's with a
שינוי. shinui היכי משני? heichi meshane? What's the שינוי shinui here? אמר
רב יוסף בכל נותן את החומץ ואחר כך נותן את השתית בשבת
נותן את השתית ואחר כך נותן
את החומץ. Amar Rav Yosef bechol noten et hachometz ve'achar kach noten
et hashatit beshabbat noten et hashatit ve'achar kach noten et hachometz. So
here the שינוי shinui. is in the way you mix the two
together, not in the way you stir them. And that's what I
told you about reversing the order. Whether first you put the vinegar
and then you put this שתית shatit or whether you put the
שתית shatit and then the vinegar. So if the normal way you
do it is that first you put the vinegar, then here first
you put the solid and then you pour the vinegar on it.
So that by the way addresses the adding of the liquid. It
doesn't exactly address why then you're allowed to stir it.
It says clearly to stir normally as long as you reverse the
order and make it loose.
Right so רש״י Rashi basically says like because it's also בלילה רכה,
belila raka, it's not really לישה at all. Of course if it's
not really לישה at all, it doesn't explain why you need to
do a שינוי shinui the way you add the liquid. So again
it's not exactly clear like what are how exactly the criteria match
up. The general rule as I told you is you sort of
incorporate pretty much all of this. You try to have all of
the קולות kulot that the גמרא Gemara said. First it's בלילה רכה,
belila raka. you switch the order of adding the liquid, you switch
the order of doing the mixing which we're going to get to
in a minute or the way of doing the mixing and so
on. But it is possible that even some of that is enough
by itself as it seems in the גמרא. Gemara No, not אדידא,
ad d'yada, that's that normally not is the one we focus on.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ברה דרב הונא
בר חייא אשכחיה לגבלא דבי נשיה דקא גביל וספי ליה לתורי. Breh
deRav Huna bar Chiyya ashkechei legavla devei nashyah deka gavil vesafi leh
letorei. So here so
the son of Rav Huna bar Chiyya found that the people working
with the animal trainers or the animal attendants in his father's house.
So it's actually interesting דבי נשא devei nasha really means is means
like the women's house and it could sometimes refer to the fact
that the father is dead. Of course we're going to see here
that the father gets into the picture, so there's an interesting discussion
about what דבי נשא devei nasha means. It's actually something we put
in the כתובה ketubah when when the father is dead and normally
the כתובה ketubah says דנהעלת ליה מבי אבוה, dena'alat leh mibei avuha,
the dowry that she brings to the marriage from her father's house.
But if the father is dead then it says מדבי נשא, midevei
nasha, from the women's house. Actually nowadays that's really supposed to just
reflect the reality so nowadays some people put in מבי אביה ואמה.
mibei aviha ve'immah. Some people say מדי נפשה, mide nafshah, she's bringing
in her own property not and so on. So actually that דבי
נשא devei nasha can be altered based on the specific circumstances. Anyway
so he found this animal attendant דקא גביל וספי ליה לתורא. deka
gavil vesafi leh letora. He was kneading the bran with the water
going back to the case in our משנה, mishnah, bran with water
and feeding it to the animals hopefully not force feeding it. Okay
so he was doing exactly what the משנה mishnah says. בטש ביה,
Batash beih, so
Rav Huna's son kicked him. Said stop doing that, you can't do
that שבת! Shabbos, Oh yes exactly. אתא אבוה אשכחיה, Ata avuha ashkechei,
so his father came and found him. אמר ליה הכי אמר אבוה
דאמך. Amar leh hachi amar avuha de'immach. Big... he
says oh you think you're so frum? Let me tell you what
your mother's father says. Again it's very interesting right because it says
דבי נשא devei nasha and now it's referring to his mother's side
of the family. So you wonder what's exactly is going on. Maybe
it was a stepfather although it doesn't say that. It said ברה
דרב הונא בר
חייא Breh deRav Huna bar Chiyya presumably talking about Rav Huna's son.
Anyway here's what your here's what your mother's father says משמיה דרב
mishmeih deRav in the name of רב. ומנו Umanu and who was
your mother's father? רבי ירמיה בר אבא. Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba. Here's
what he says: גובלין ולא מספין ודלא לקיט בלישניה מחלקיטין ליה. Govlin
velo masfin vedela lakit bilshoneih machalkitin leh.
So you can first of all you can mix, you can be
גובל, govel, you can mix the water with the bran like our
משנה mishnah says. You can't be מספי, maspi, feed it into the
animal's mouth. Oh this guy was feeding it into the animal's mouth.
So first of all רש״י Rashi says the מספין masfin is the
thing in the משנה mishnah which before sort of was the force
feed okay. And number two it also says דלא לקיט בלישניה, dela
lakit bilshoneih, if the calf is young and he cannot actually lick
it up with its own tongue swallow use its own tongue to
swallow מחלקיטין ליה, machalkitin leh,
then you can help feed it, you can help help it swallow.
Okay so anyway so why are you giving him a hard time?
He's doing exactly what's allowed. Now the גמרא Gemara adds presumably this
next line is the גמרא's Gemara gloss not what was said והני
מילי
דמשני. Vehani mili dameshany. One minute, the גמרא Gemara keeps on jumping
in, right? מותר, מותר, the גמרא Gemara keeps on jumping in. Oh,
you have to do at least a שינוי. shinui Okay, so היכי
משני? heichi meshani?
Now how do you do the שינוי? By the way, I misstated
it. The משנה Mishnah doesn't say he did more than the משנה.
Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says, right, what does the משנה Mishnah say?
נותנין מים למורסן אבל לא גובלין, nostnim maim le-mursan aval lo govlin,
I'm sorry, I misstated. The משנה Mishnah says לא גובלין. lo govlin.
Here it really seems to be highly problematic, because right here he
was actually גובל, govel, he actually kneaded it. Okay, so that was
against the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says, oh no, you're
allowed to be גובל. govel. Why? And then it goes back to
what everything we've been saying until now, that sometimes we actually allow
you to do the actual kneading if you do it with a
שינוי. Okay, so until now what has the שינוי been that we
have said? Maybe a little at a time. We spoke about a
שינוי in terms of the order, but that's only in the mixing.
Here we're talking about a שינוי in the actual, in the actual
kneading. So what's the... היכי משני? How do you do a שינוי?
אמר רב יימר בר שלמיא משמיה דאביי: Amar Rav Yeimar bar Shmaya
mishmei de-Abaye: שתי וערב. shesi ve-erev.
So
you do it sort of, you know, warp and woof. So basically
what that means is, right, if this is your, if this is
your thing, you know, normally the way you would stir is you'd
just do like that, sort of like, you know, elliptical motions. No,
you have to do one direction, pick it out, and do the
other direction. Like that. Keep on doing like a plus sign. Okay,
it's very laborious. And it's not so effective, because it only, you
know, it doesn't get to all parts of the...
but you can't rotate it?
Well, that's true. So then that's what the גמרא Gemara says: והא
לא מיערב שפיר. ve-ha lo mearev shapira. It doesn't get mixed well.
אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: מנער ליה לכלי. menaaro li-kli. All
right, so what you could also do is pour it from one
vessel to the other, like you know, so it sort of gets
all mixed up, but you cannot do the normal, normal kneading. So
what have we said? We basically have said a lot of stuff,
and it's slightly unclear to know exactly what the bottom line is.
But we've said that there's a debate about whether you can even
add the water that רבי Rebbe? does not like that. רבי Rabbi,
יוסי ברבי יהודה says it's okay. We've seen that there are times
where we allow you to add it with reversing the order, presumably
that's according to רבי. Rabbi. We've also seen that there are times
where we allow you actually to do the kneading itself by some
type of a שינוי, either with a little bit at a time
or here we talked about a שינוי of the actual stirring, maybe
only combined with the idea that it's a loose type of a
בלילה רכה, although this case where he was adding water to the
bran would seem to be a בלילה עבה, would seem to be
a thick mixture. So again, not exactly clear how all of those
factor together, but what we did have was this case, this actual
real case, which was even more lenient than the משנה. Mishnah. The
משנה Mishnah says add the water not mixed, and here this guy
was actually, the guy who was attending the animals actually mixed it,
which led to this strong response. And then the גמרא Gemara says
actually it is okay as long as you do a שינוי.
Yes, it's opposed to some other cases where you know, גזרה gezeira
one thing for another, but here no one's going to be גוזר
gozer adding some liquid to another liquid because you'll come to add
a liquid to a solid or whatever.
Yeah, you know, I don't know what to tell you. I mean,
for some reason like I said, we have protections on protections on
protections, and here we're allowing a דאורייתא with a שינוי. Now again,
some... there's some pushback, and the גמרא Gemara keeps on insisting שינוי,
so at least it's more limited than it sounded like the initial
statement which was even without a שינוי, which is hard to even
imagine. I will tell you probably the explanation of the simple read
of these things that said without a שינוי is going back to
the issue the גמרא Gemara, said before about לאו בר גיבול. lav
bar gibbul. That if it's a type of a thing like bran
or whatever that does not dissolve well and does not turn into
a type of a doughy mixture, maybe that would not be biblical
לישה. But the גמרא Gemara pushes back and the גמרא Gemara insists
that you have some שינוי. And then we try to combine all
of the, you know, sort of things. A שינוי and a בלילה
רכה. But yeah, it's very strange that we allow this
stuff לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Yeah.
Does שינוי apply also to the בר גיבול bar gibbul or is
it just if it's only for the לאו בר? lav bar?
We assume that it's even if it's a בר גיבול. bar gibbul.
It's true you could have tried to say that all the cases
in the גמרא Gemara so far were לאו בר גיבול, lav bar
gibbul, and that, and maybe that's only why we allow it, but
we, we don't make that distinction. So now the גמרא gemara says
like this.
כתב אפנקסיה דזעירי. Kesav apinkasei di-Zeiri. It was written on like the
notebook of זעירי. Zeiri. Now this is very interesting because it speaks
about something written in an oral culture. רש"י Rashi actually says where
it says פנקסיה, pinkasei, רש"י Rashi says, where's
רש"י? Rashi? אפנקסיה, apinkasei, about ten lines down in the narrow lines,
לוחות קשורות זו עם זו כאותן של סוחרים. luchot keshurot zu im
zu ke-otan shel socharim. Basically you have like you know,
big covers,
you know, bound together and obviously presumably papers on the inside. So,
anyway, you have a notebook. So it was written in the notebook
of זעירי: Zeiri:
אמרית קמיה דרבי. amrit kamei de-Rebbe. I said in front of רבי.
Rabbi ומנו? u-manu? And who was my רבי? רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
I said to him: מהו לגבי? ma-u legabbei? Can you do גיבול?
gibbul? Can you actually, you know, mix the water with the bran?
אמר אסור. Amar assur. No, you can't. Okay, that's the משנה. Mishnah.
You can't do גיבול. gibbul. The גמרא Gemara only pushed back and
said maybe with a שינוי. But anyway, he, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
said אסור. assur. מהו לפרק? ma-u lefarek? How about unloading? Now what
does unloading mean? רש"י Rashi says it means transferring fruit from one
animal to across to another one, which as you might remember discussed
in an earlier משנה. Mishnah. תוספות Tosafot says, there's a different explanation.
He says that, that it means actually...
what we talked about before, that you're in a way of mixing
it, how about which is in the same context, rather than stirring
it normally, you sort of turn it from one vessel to the
next and mix it by pouring it from one vessel to the
next. אמר מותר. Amar mutar. Okay, that's allowed. אמר רב מנשיא Amar
Rav Menashya so said רב מנשיא, Rav Menashya,
this part is on the פנקס pinkas too, right? Just the...
Right, right, right. And now it goes on.
It's strange that רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, this guy who came with
the... grandson of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, grandson of
רבי חייא בר חייא. Rabbi Chiyya bar Chiyya.
Right, right.
If it's the same רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, could be, you're right.
So that's interesting. So maybe that's the point. Maybe that's why he
was going with his grandfather's position. Oh but that's an interesting point.
If it's the same רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, so he was following
his paternal grandfather's position and his father actually said, but on your
other side, your maternal grandfather allows it. That's interesting. That's interesting. Okay,
I didn't think about that. So אמר רב מנשיא, Amar Rav Menashya,
חד כמי חד, chad kammai chad, now that we're talking about putting
food in front of animals,
he says you could put one sort of
troughful in front of one animal, תרי כמי תרי trei kammai trei
and two in front of two,
אבל שפיר דמי, aval shapir dami, that's good. תלתא כמי תרי tlata
kammai trei however three sort of troughs in front of two animals,
אסור. So we're back to just feeding animals and the טרחא tircha
issue involved with that.
Okay, so and רש"י Rashi says it means like the standard amount
of unit you put in front of one, you can put in
front of it, but you can't put more than the standard, even
three in front of two, let alone two in front of one.
רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, רב יוסף Rav Yosef said there
is no limit. קב ואפילו קביים, kav va'afilu kabayim, you can put
even a קב, kav, even two קביים. kabayim. עולא אמר כור ואפילו
כוריים, Ulla amar kur va'afilu kurayim, one כור, kur, even two כוריים.
kurayim. Okay, so that was a little digression about טרחא tircha and
how much food you put in front of animals.
כור Kur is a lot of food.
I know. Okay. כתיב אפנקסיה דלוי. Kesiv apinkasei deLevi. Okay, now we're
back to, we're back to notebooks and גיבול. gibbul. So it was
written on the פנקס pinkas of לוי. Levi. אמרית קמיה דרבי, Amrit
kamei deRabbi, I said in front of
רבי, ומנו רבנו הקדוש, Umanu Rabbeinu Hakadosh, the who was that, רבנו
הקדוש Rabbeinu Hakadosh is a גמרא Gemara gloss. He didn't have to
write in his own פנקס, pinkas, who do I mean when I
say רבי. Okay. So I said in front of רבי יהודה הנשיא,
Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, אדבבו גבלין שתיתא בבבל. adbbavu gavlin shatisa beVavel. I
mentioned to him that in בבל Bavel they allowed people to actually
knead this שתית, shatis, this bran with water on שבת, Shabbos, presumably
with a שינוי like we discussed before. וצווח רבי, Vetzavach Rabbi, and
my רבי would be yelling. ומנו רבנו הקדוש, Umanu Rabbeinu Hakadosh, by
the way in case you forgot that's רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi. I don't know why he had to repeat it twice. אדבבו
גבלין שתיתא, Adbbavu gavlin shatisa, he was, he would be so enraged
that they would be kneading this bran on שבת, Shabbos ולית דשמיע
ליה, Velais deshmia lei, and nobody would listen to him. So you
have examples in the גמרא Gemara whatever about the many times that
people would like try to protest what they thought is forbidden behavior
and it would do no good. The same guy? Yeah, yeah. It's
funny why he had to repeat it twice. Okay. ולית חילי בידיה
למיסר, Velais cheilei bidei lemisar, and he did not have the ability
to try to use his authority to forbid it, even though he
was trying to persuade them to stop, he could not be more
forceful, מדיוסי ברבי יהודה, Mide'Yosei bar'Rabbi Yehuda, because of רב יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rav Yosei bar'Rabbi Yehuda who is of the more lenient position
about, about לישה. Now again, רב יוסי ברבי יהודה Rav Yosei bar'Rabbi
Yehuda is only of the lenient position about adding the liquid, right?
But here what we're doing is, once he was lenient about that,
somehow as long as you could add the liquid, then it also
as we saw in the earlier גמרא, Gemara there were opinions that
you could actually mix it as long as you incorporated a שינוי
with the mixing. But clearly we're seeing here that there is a
pushback to that approach.
רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi accepted רב's position that it wasn't...
Yes. It's okay, but you know that gets to the general dialectic
between the common practice and the פסק הלכה. psak halacha. And sometimes
there are other rabbinic positions, so maybe that gave greater force to
רב יוסי ברבי יהודה's Rav Yosei bar'Rabbi Yehuda position because that was
how the people were practicing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
כתיב אפנקסיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי. Kesiv apinkasei deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
Now that we're talking about things in notebooks, so now this is
not לוי's Levi פנקס pinkas but his son's, רבי יהושע בן לוי's
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi פנקס. pinkas. Here's what was written on his
little notebook. And this is going to have nothing to do with
anything that we've discussed. It's actually a fascinating גמרא Gemara but completely
unrelated to שבת Shabbat. or to kneading dough. האי מאן דבחד בשבתא,
Hai man devachad beshabba, if somebody is born on Sunday, יהא גבר.
yehei gavar. He will be a real person. בלא חדא בי, Belo
chada bei, without anything else, without another thing in him. So it's
a little ambiguous what that means, the גמרא Gemara, will explain. Right,
well whatever. בלא חדא בי מאי בלא חדא בי? Belo chada bei
mai belo chada bei? What does that thing mean? אילימא בלא חד
לטיבו, Eilima belo chad letivu, he is going to be all wicked.
והאמר רב אשי אנא בחד בשבתא הואי, Veha'amar Rav Ashi ana bachad
beshabba havai, רב אשי Rav Ashi said I was born on Sunday.
So clearly a person born on Sunday can't always be wicked. אלא
לאו חד לבישו, Ella lav chad levishu, not
even one character of not even one bad bad character of his,
characteristic of him. That can't be. והאמר רב אשי, Veha'amar Rav Ashi,
the same רב אשי Rav Ashi said, אנא ודימי בר קקוזתא, ana
u'Dimi bar Kakuzta, I and דימי בר קקוזתא, Dimi bar Kakuzta, never
heard of him before, you'll find out why in a minute, הויין
בחד בשבתא, haviyan bachad beshabba, we were both born on a Sunday,
אנא מלך והוא הוי ריש גנבי. ana melech vehu havai reish ganavei.
I was like the king, meaning like the head of a ישיבה,
yeshiva, and he was the head bandit. So you're going to be
like a head, you'll... be an important person, but not necessarily good
or bad, I mean, good or bad, it's not one clear, it's
not clearly going to be one or the other.
I don't know how
רב אסי Rav Assi
knows this guy so well.
I know. אלא, Ela, איכולי לטיבו איכולי לבישו. ikulei l'tivu ikulei l'bishu.
Fine. What it means is you'll be a real important person, either
all bad or all good. Okay, and that's what's בלא חדא בי.
v'lo chada bei. You won't have one of the other things, you'll
be fully on one side of the force. Okay. Now the Gemara
by the way says in parentheses, so I'll take this out, מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? דאישתכללו ביה אור וחושך, d'ishtachlalu bei
or v'choshech, because on Sunday is, you know, light and dark. It's
on—it's they're all one or all the other. Rashi doesn't—it seems like
he doesn't have that. He just says Sunday is the first of
the days, so it means you're the first, you're important. Okay. האי
מן דבתרי בשבתא, Hai man d'bisrei b'shabasa, somebody born on a Monday,
יהא גבר רגזן, yehei gvar ragzan, will be an angry person. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? משום דאיפליגו ביה מיא, mishum d'ipligu bei maya,
because the waters were split, so there's like contention, they had to
be taken apart. האי מן דבתלתא בשבתא, Hai man d'bitlasa b'shabasa, somebody
born on a Tuesday, יהא גבר עתיר וזנאי, yehei gvar atir v'zanai,
will be rich and promiscuous. עתיר Atir rich, וזנאי v'zanai promiscuous. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? משום דאיברו ביה דשאים, mishum d'ivru bei d'shaim,
because of the grass. So what does that have to do with
grass? So Rashi says, you know, because grass sort of like it
grows quickly and it grows all over the place, and therefore, you
know, we actually use promiscuous in that way, like you talk about
promiscuous growth of a garden, you know, in a garden or something
when the plants are getting out of hand. So anyway, so that's
why and rich presumably also because it just happens so quickly and
it spreads. So this sense of wealth and increase. האי מן דבארבע
בשבתא, Hai man d'b'arba b'shabasa, somebody born on a Wednesday, יהא גבר
חכים ונהיר, yehei gvar chakim v'nahir, will be wise and Rashi says
like bright or, you know, shining, some say נהיר nahir here means
to have a good memory. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why? משום דאיתלו
ביה מאורות, mishum d'islu bei meoros, because of the, you know, of
the luminaries. So the sense of the sun and, you know, the
source—light is a source of wisdom, etc. האי מן דבחמשה בשבתא, Hai
man d'bachamisha b'shabasa, somebody born on Thursday, יהא גבר גומל חסדים, yehei
gvar gomel chasadim, somebody who does acts of kindness. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? Why? משום דאיברו ביה דגים ועופות, mishum d'ivru bei dagim v'ofos,
because of the fish and the birds. Where's that גומל חסדים? gomel
chasadim? So Rashi says fish and birds don't have to go around
as much as certain other animals to find their food, it's more
readily available for them, somehow that symbolizes the sense of, you know,
providing for people. The same way God provides for the fish and
the birds. האי מן דבמעלי שבתא, Hai man d'b'ma'alei shabasa, somebody born
on a Friday, יהא גבר חזרן, yehei gvar chazran, will be a
person that's always like, you know, running after things. Like Rashi says
because that's what you do on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. You're always
running around getting ready for שבת. Shabbat, So אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, it's so funny because a lot
of things got done on—once you're talking about מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit
rather than running around on שבת, Shabbat, you know there's animals, there's
people, there's a lot of things, anyway,
חזרן במצוות, chazran b'mitzvos, specifically about מצוות. mitzvos. Rashi says מצוות mitzvos
sometimes in a particular context means about צדקה. tzedakah. So specifically somebody
that's always looking for opportunities to give צדקה. tzedakah. I lost my
place. Where was I? So
hold on, let me just check.
No, I'm sorry. No, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, that's a later Rashi
where he says מצוות mitzvos means צדקה. tzedakah. Here he just says
it means in general you'll be seeking out opportunities to do מצוות
mitzvos because the running around you do on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
is in preparation for a מצוה. mitzvah. Somebody on Friday is always
seeking out opportunities maybe particularly for מצוות. mitzvos. האי מן דבשבתא, Hai
man d'bishabasa, somebody born on a
שבת, Shabbat יהא בשבתא ימות. yehei bishabasa yamis. On שבת Shabbat. he
will die. יהא בשבתא ימות. yehei bishabasa yamis. He'll be a person
that will die on שבת. Shabbat. Why? על דאחילו עלוהי יומא רבא
דשבתא, Al d'achilu alohi yoma raba d'shabasa, because because of him they
had to be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat when he was born, which
is very strange. First of all, right, is he being punished? I
mean the Gemara sort of sees this all as these, you know,
somehow it's like an automatic like, you know, type of an, I
don't know, metaphysical reality, but also why is it considered חילול שבת?
chilul Shabbat? I mean, you know, it's a מצוה mitzvah to save
a life on שבת. Shabbat. So there's then so there's a pushback
then. The Gemara says the immediate next line is אמר רבא בר
רב שילא וקדישא רבא יתקרי. Amar Rava bar Rav Shila v'kadisha raba
yitkeri. Okay, but he'll also be called the great holy one because
he was born on שבת. Shabbat, So, you know, two very different
approaches to looking at that. אמר להו רבי חנינא. Amar lehu Rabbi
Chanina. So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said after this was read from
the פנקס pinkas of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
So he said the following. One minute, I just want to
see. Where was... yes. So he said to the students who basically
told him that this was on the פנקס pinkas of רבי יהושע
בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, אמר להו רבי חנינא פוקו אמרו
ליה לבר ליואי, Amar lehu Rabbi Chanina puku imru lei l'bar Liva'i,
go tell the son of Levi, רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi who wrote all of this down in his notebook, לא
מזל יום גורם, lo mazal yom gorem, I gotta tell you buddy,
it's not the מזל, mazal, the, you know, sign, the astronomical significance
of the day that you were born that influences you, אלא מזל
שעה גורם. ela mazal sha'ah gorem. It's the influence of the hour,
of the, you know, of the stars and what their ascendancy was...
what?
You didn't see that one?
Yeah, you didn't see that one coming. אלא, Ela, you know, הכל
בבחירה חופשית hakol b'bechirah chofshit or הכל בידי שמים... hakol biyedei shamayim...
No, no, no.
This is עבודה זרה! Avodah Zarah!
It's not עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. I'll talk about—let me read a
little and then I'll say some words.
What about the seasons? Were they...
that's a... right. Let me read a little and then I'll say
something about it. Okay. Now, the order of that was understood that
there were seven celestial bodies and they went in some rotation each
one at a different hour of the day. So since a day
doesn't have is not 24 hours is not divisible by seven, based
on the day of the week, it's not the same for every
hour. 6:00 AM on Monday is different than 6:00 AM on Tuesday.
Anyway, Steinsaltz has a whole chart so you can know exactly which
day, which hour is which מזל. mazal. Okay, so anyway, so האי
מאן דבחמה, hai man de-be-chama, somebody born under the constellation of the
sun, יהא גבר זיותן, yehei gavar zivtan, will be a person of
like shining. יהא אכיל מדיליה, yehei achil mi-dilei, he'll eat from his
own food, the same way the sun provides light, it's self-sustaining and
it provides for everyone else, so he'll eat from his own food,
ושתא מדיליה, ve-shata mi-dilei, he'll drink from his own, ורזוהי גליין, ve-razohi
galyan, but he won't have any, you know, he won't be able
to keep any secrets, all of his secrets will be revealed, the
same way the sun everything is out in the open, you know,
it's all gives light to everyone, there's nothing hidden about it. אם
גניב לא מצלח, im ganiv lo matzlach, and therefore if he's a
גנב, ganav, he won't be successful because he won't be able to
keep anything hidden. האי מאן דכוכב נוגה, hai man de-chochav noga, somebody
born under נוגה, noga, which is Venus, which comes after sun, יהא
גבר עתיר וזנאי. yehei gavar atir ve-zanai. He'll again, be rich and
promiscuous. יהא זנאי? yehei zanai?
Wait, I thought this guy on the Sunday was the chief גנב
ganav though?
I don't know what to tell you.
We had that before.
Yeah, I understand. But so this is a different opinion. This is
the guy saying it's not מזל יום, mazal yom, it's מזל שעה.
mazal sha'ah. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? Maybe they were
both born under
Venus? מאי טעמא mai ta'ama משום דאיתילד בנורא, mishum de-ityalid be-nura, because
a fire is lit within him. Somehow Venus represents fire, I'm not
exactly sure why.
Anyway, and somehow so he has a fire burning within him, so
that leads him to being like more promiscuous.
Is that considered a negative?
Well, the זנאי, zanai, promiscuous, seems
they may not mean that.
I don't know, possibly. Rashi says even more specifically an adulterer, but
you know, I don't know any גמרא Gemara that does not interpret
it in a negative way. But you'd have to look.
So why would he be wealthy?
I also guess like, I don't know, the fire's burning, it means
that you're, you know, you've got a lot of passion. It's sort
of like, what is it with Freud about? What does it do
with wealth? Yeah, I don't know, you're going out and doing things
in the world. I'm not exactly sure. Okay, anyway, moving on.
Moving on.
Let's see if Rashi says. אש תלויה בו, esh teluya bo, no,
Rashi says יתר תשמיש. yeter tashmish. Okay, anyway, moving on. האי מאן
דכוכב, hai man de-chochav,
somebody born under כוכב chochav by itself, which means Mercury, will be
now Mercury is the closest planet to the sun so will be
a person that's shining, because Mercury is close to the sun, וחכים,
ve-chakim, and smart, משום דספרא דחמה הוא, mishum de-safra de-chama hu,
because it's like he's the scribe of the sun. He always goes
next to the sun, keeping down like he's the, you know, he's
the secretary of the sun. Okay, so somehow he's very similar to
the sun in that way of sense of having all this, you
know, all of the, you know, light that the sun gives off.
In Greek mythology Mercury is the messenger.
Right.
Oh, that's interesting. That's interesting. Maybe there's an echo of that. האי
מאן דבלבנה, hai man de-bi-levana, somebody born under the moon, יהא גבר
סביל מרעין, yehei gavar sevil marin, somebody that suffers much evil, because
you know, the moon constantly waxes and wanes. בנוי וסתיר סתיר ובנוי,
banui ve-satir satir ve-banui,
builds and destroys, destroys and builds. אכיל דלאו דיליה, achil de-lav dilei,
eats things that aren't his because the sun, moon's light is not
its own, ושתא דלאו דיליה, ve-shata de-lav dilei, he drinks things that
are not his, ורזוהי כסיין, ve-razohi kasyan,
his secrets will be hidden because you know, like the moon is
often not visible. אם גנב מצלח, im ganav matzlach,
and if he's a גנב, ganav, he'll be successful because his secrets
will be hidden, and maybe that ties into food that's not his
own. Rashi also says the idea of not his own is because
sometimes the moon is seen in the day, but presumably more simply
it means that the light is not its own. האי מאן דשבתאי,
hai man de-shabtai, somebody born under Saturn, יהא גבר מחשבתיה בטלין, yehei
gavar machshavteih betalin, somebody whose thoughts will be negated. Rashi just says
it's like a word of שבת, Shabbat שבתאי, shabtai, like, you know,
ceased. So he won't succeed. ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika de-amri, some say the
opposite. כל דמחשבין עליה בטלין, kol de-machshevin aleih betalin, anybody that plans
against him, their plans will be negated. האי מאן דבצדק, hai man
de-vitzedek, somebody born under Jupiter, יהא גבר צדקן, yehei gavar tzadkan, will
be a righteous person. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, וצדקן במצות, ve-tzadkan be-mitzvot, specifically here Rashi says מצות mitzvot
means in giving charity. האי מאן דבמאדים, hai man de-ve-ma'adim, somebody born
under Mars, this is now this line is very famous, people know
this, יהא גבר אשיר דמי, yehei gavar ashir dami, will be a
spiller of blood. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, אי אומנא אי
גנבא, ei umna ei ganva,
may okay, but how you direct that depends on you. Maybe you'll
that's my read into it maybe you'll be a bloodletter like a
doctor, maybe you'll be a גנבא, ganva, somebody who kills, you know,
אי טבחא, ei tavcha, maybe you'll be a ritual slaughterer, אי מהולא,
ei mahola, or maybe you'll be a מוהל. mohel. So you know,
this is nice if you sort of bracket the whole astrology part
of it, which is hard to bracket, I'll get back to that
in a minute, but if you talk about the fact that you
know, everybody is born I mean, there's other גמרות gemarot that talk
about like, you know, that like right before an infant is, you
know, when an infant is conceived, the angel says to God, will
he be rich, will he be poor, will he be this type
or that type, and all of it is predetermined, but
except for צדיק או רשע, tzadik o rasha, because that's all in
your in your, you know, in your hands. So while the idea
of predetermination or of astrology is not something that we tend to
like or accept, the idea that a lot of who we are
is predetermined in terms of our genetics and our upbringing and our
socioeconomic status, you know, so a similar point could be made. You
see people have different inclinations and different, you know, and different types
of personalities, but you still can choose like how to direct it
and how to use it. So it doesn't, you know, so, so
that is a sort of nice way of reframing, you know, or
applying this statement about Rav Nachman bar about, about the Mars and
the blood in Rav Ashi's statement in a sort of in a
more contemporary way. Now אמר רבא, Amar Rava, Rava said, אנא במאדים
הואי, Ana b'Ma'adim havai, I was born under Mars, and I'm not
any of those. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מר נמי עניש וקטיל.
Mar nami anish v'katil. The master also, he, you know, punishes people
in his, you know, presumably role as a דיין dayan and kills.
Now that's fascinating. Did they really execute people for, you know, at
that time? But anyway, it sounds like it. Anyway, so as a
דיין dayan you also lead to the spilling of blood and so
it's also you redirect your violence. איתמר... Itmar...
Well, another interesting note over here that Rava killed Rav Zeira.
Oh, that's interesting. Okay. Okay, so not as a דיין dayan you
mean, just whatever he gave him the evil eye type of a
thing.
No, it's in the famous
thing in the מגילה Megillah on פורים.
Purim. I know. Oh, that's true. All right. It wasn't the evil
eye, that was a different story. Right, that's true. Then why would
it say עניש? anish? But okay, anyway, but that's a good point.
Okay, so before he killed him... Right, right. איתמר, Itmar, רבי חנינא
אומר, Rabbi Chanina omer, מזל מחכים
מזל מעשיר. mazal machkim mazal ma'ashir. So summing up what we said
before, right, the מזל mazal makes you smart or makes you rich,
meaning influences your destiny, ויש מזל לישראל v'yesh mazal l'Yisrael and it
even applies to Jews. רבי יוחנן אומר... Rabbi Yochanan omer... now by
the way, Rabbi Chanina I believe is the one that said הכל
בידי שמים חוץ
מיראת שמים. hakol bidei shamayim chutz me'yirat shamayim. So again, people try
to qualify that somewhat. It doesn't mean completely determined, but anyway, strong,
certainly heavily influences.
Is this different than what we were saying before? No, מזל mazal
is that the season as opposed to before?
No, it's the same thing we're saying before. It's just summing it
up and now it's getting to the point about whether it applies
even to Jews, because the גמרא Gemara? until now has been assuming
it applies to Jews. So he says, yeah, all of that has
a strong influence, maybe not completely determinant, but certainly a strong influence
and it applies to Jews. רבי יוחנן אומר אין מזל לישראל. Rabbi
Yochanan omer ein mazal l'Yisrael. No, I'm sorry, it doesn't affect Jews.
ואף רבי יוחנן לטעמיה V'af Rabbi Yochanan l'taimei goes according to his
reasoning, דאמר רבי יוחנן מניין שאין מזל לישראל. d'amar Rabbi Yochanan minayin
she'ein mazal l'Yisrael. How do we know there isn't מזל mazal to
Jews? שנאמר כה אמר ה׳ אל דרך הגוים אל תלמדו. shene'emar Ko
amar Hashem el derech hagoyim al tilmadu. So says God, do not
learn by the ways of the non-Jews. ומאותות השמים אל תחתו. umi'otot
hashamayim al techattu. Do not fear from the signs of heaven, which
means the astro, you know, the planets or whatever should not, don't
fear their influence. כי יחתו הגוים מהמה. ki chattu hagoyim mehema. המה
יחתו ולא ישראל. hema yechettu v'lo Yisrael. Because the גוים goyim will
fear them, they have to worry about them, not us. רב סבר
אין מזל לישראל. Rav savar ein mazal l'Yisrael. Rav also felt, believes
that there is no... these constellations don't influence Jews. דאמר רב יהודה
אמר רב מניין... D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav minayin... oh again, don't
have that strong of an influence, we'll see about that in a
minute. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, because
this famous statement of Rav, quoted by רש״י Rashi in the חומש,
Chumash, מניין שאין מזל לישראל, minayin she'ein mazal l'Yisrael, how do we
know? שנאמר ויוצא אתו החוצה. Shene'emar vayotze oto hachutza. God takes אברם
Avram outside and tells him, like, look at the stars and this
will be your seed. אמר אברם לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Avram
lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu, Avram said to God, רבונו של עולם בן
ביתי יורש אותי. Ribono shel Olam ben beiti yoresh oti. He says,
you know, what? My, you know,
like אליעזר, Eliezer, you know, the servant in my house is going
to inherit me? אמר לו לאו, Amar lo lav, no, כי אם
אשר יצא ממעיך. ki im asher yetze mime'echa. Only someone of your
loins. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, so he said, רבונו של עולם נסתכלתי
באצטגנינות שלי. Ribono shel Olam nistakalti be'itz tagninut sheli. I looked in
my astrology, ואיני רואה להוליד בן. v'eini ro'eh leholid ben. I'm not
going to give birth to a son. אמר לו צא מאיצטגנינות שלך.
Amar leh tze me'itz tagninut shelcha. Forget about your astrology, get out
of there. החוצה, Hachutza, it doesn't have an influence on you. שאין
מזל לישראל. she'ein mazal l'Yisrael. Because there's no מזל לישראל. mazal l'Yisrael.
מה דעתך? Ma da'atach? What do you think? דקאי צדק במערבא? Dekai
tzedek be'ma'arava? צדק, Tzedek,
which apparently was אברם's Avram
astrological sign. Now imagine אברם Avram and שרה Sarah had a date,
"So what's your sign?" So anyway,
his sign was צדק, tzedek, so that your concerned is that that's
במערבא, be'ma'arava, that was in the west, maybe when you were born
or something, and if it's in the west that's like רש״י Rashi
says, it's cooler in the west because sun rises in the east,
so anyway somehow the fact that it was in the west is
going to influence. מהדרינא ומוקמינא לה במזרח. Mahadrina u'mokeimna leh be'mizrach. All
right, I'll move the star, the entire constellation to the east. והיינו
דכתיב. Vehainu d'ichtiv. Again, I don't know exactly when it gets moved
or whatever. Anyway, and that's what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, מי
העיר ממזרח צדק יקראהו לרגלו. Mi he'ir mi'mizrach tzedek yikra'ehu l'raglo. Like,
who is the one that bestirred from the east? Right, it's a
הפטרה haftarah of that פרשה. parsha. Who is the one that was
bestirred from the east? Or assume that's אברהם Avraham who came from
the east from ארם נהרים, Aram Naharayim, but here it's saying, no,
God, you know, called צדק לרגלו, tzedek l'raglo, צדק, tzedek, Jupiter, יקראהו
לרגלו, yikra'ehu l'raglo, called for the sake of אברם Avram to come
over to the east. By the way, I will say that רש״י
Rashi on the חומש Chumash says,
ends it differently. If people remember the רש״י on the חומש, Chumash,
he says, אברם אינו מוליד אבל אברהם מוליד. Avram eino molid aval
Avraham molid. Of course, and that's why you're getting an extra ה.
hei. Of course what that means is you're not totally above the
astrology. The astrology is still right, we just have to change it.
Here also the גמרא Gemara. says something like that. It's not completely
unrelated, God will change the astrology. but yes, the astrology does have
these clear influences.
This
is the underpinnings of what we do when we change someone's name
when they're desperately ill, right?
Yeah, I mean, is it related to, is it related, okay, we
can talk about that whether it's related, it necessarily is about astrological
beliefs. I don't think it has to be related to that per
se, but you're right, somehow it is connected. ומידשמואל נמי אין מזל
mazal לישראל *Umid'Shmuel nami ein mazal l'Yisrael*, from שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* you
can also see there's no מזל לישראל *mazal l'Yisrael*. שמואל Shmuel ואבלט
*Shmuel v'Avlat*, from שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* and אבלט *Avlat* who was a
non-Jewish astrologer. הוו יתבי והוו יתבי *Havu yasvi v'havu yasvi* were sitting.
והוו קאזלי הנך אינשי לאגמא *V'havu ka'azli hanach inshi l'agma*, and certain
people were going to the lake or the pond. אמר ליה אבלט
לשמואל *Amar lei Avlat l'Shmuel*, so אבלט *Avlat* said to שמואל *Shmuel*:
האי גברא אזיל *Hai gavra azil*, that person who's going, I know
based on his astrological sign or whatever, and he's going ולא אתי
*v'lo asi*, he won't come back. טרקא ליה חיויא ומיית *Tarka lei
chivya u'mayis*, a snake will bite him and he'll die. אמר ליה
שמואל *Amar lei Shmuel*, אי בר ישראל Yisrael הוא *ei bar Yisrael
hu*, if he's Jewish, אזיל ואתי *azil v'asi*, he'll go and come
back. Okay, ועד יתבי *v'ad yasvi*, while they were sitting, אזיל ואתי
*azil v'asi*, he went and he came back. קם אבלט שדייה לטוניה
*Kam Avlat shadyei l'tunei*, so אבלט *Avlat* got up, threw the guy's
like load off of him, you know, because apparently I don't know
somehow he not only knew he was going to get bitten by
a snake but somehow knew the snake would be in his in
his load. אשכח ביה חיויא *Ashkach bei chivya*, and he saw a
snake דפסיק ושדי בתרתי גופי *d'pasik v'shadi b'sarti gufei*, that was cut
into two בתרתי גופי *b'sarti gufei*, was cut into two halves. So
somehow the snake was ready to bite him and something happened as
they were chopping wood or whatever they were doing that they accidentally
killed the snake. אמר ליה שמואל *Amar lei Shmuel*, so שמואל *Shmuel*
said, מאי עבדת *mai avadat*, what did you do? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, כל יומא הוה רמינן ריפתא בהדי הדדי *kol yoma hava raminan
rifta bahadi hadadi*, every day what we would do is everybody would
sort of like contribute bread to a communal basket, ואכלינן *v'achlinan*, and
we would eat it. האידנא הוה איכא חד מינן *Haidna hava ika
chad minan*, now today there was one of us דלא הוה ליה
ריפתא *d'lo hava lei rifta*, he had no bread to contribute. הוה
קא מיכסיף *Hava ka michsif*, he was embarrassed like apparently other people
didn't know and he was very anxious what was going to happen
when they did the collection. אמינא להו אנא *Amina lehu ana*, I
said to the group, אנא קאימנא ורמינא *ana kaimna v'ramina*, I'll go
and I'll collect the bread from everyone. כי מטאי לגביה *Ki matai
lgabeih*, when I came to him, שוואי נפשאי כמאן דשקיל מיניה *shavai
nafshai k'man d'shakil mineih*, I made it look like I was I
was taking bread from him, but I wasn't. Now רש"י *Rashi* said
okay but you're still stealing from everybody else, so רש"י *Rashi* says
okay I gave my own bread in in his stead, okay which
isn't in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, כי היכי דלא ליכסיף *ki heichi
d'lo lichsif*, so he shouldn't be embarrassed. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, so
שמואל *Shmuel* said, מצוה עבדת *mitzvah avadat*, oh, you did a מצוה
*mitzvah*. נפק שמואל ודרש *Nafak Shmuel v'darash*, and that's what led to
this so שמואל *Shmuel* went out and he and he expounded: וצדקה
תציל ממות *u'tzedakah tatzil mi'mavet*, צדקה *tzedakah* saves from death. ולא ממיתה
משונה *v'lo mimisah meshunah*, not just from a like from a, you
know, an unusual death, a painful death, which is how another גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* explains it because everybody's going to die, so it means
it saves you from a painful death, אלא ממיתה עצמה *ela mimisah
atzmah*, really saves you from a death, the death that was predestined
that would have happened to you. If you do an act of
צדקה *tzedakah*, you can be saved from it. Now of course again
it seems like it's not like the מזל *mazal* had no influence,
it would he might have happened had he not done this act
of צדקה *tzedakah*. It also raises questions that why שמואל *Shmuel* said
oh if he's a Jew he'll come back because now it seems
like the only way he came back was not because it wasn't
had no influence at all on him but because he actually had
an opportunity to transcend the מזל *mazal*, but how did שמואל *Shmuel*
know he would definitely come back? I don't know. So anyway ומדרבי
עקיבא נמי אין מזל לישראל *umiderabbi Akiva nami ein mazal l'Yisrael*, from
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* you also find this. דרבי עקיבא הויא ליה
ברתא *D'Rabbi Akiva havya lei barta*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* had a
daughter. אמרו ליה כלדאי Kaldayei *Amru lei kalda'ei*, so the כלדאי Kaldayei
*kalda'ei*, who were astrologers, said to him, ההוא יומא דעיילה לבי גננא
*hahu yoma d'aylah l'vei ganana*, the day that she gets under the
חופה *chuppah*, טרקא לה חיויא ומיתה *tarka lah chivya u'misa*, a snake
will bite her once again and she'll die. הוה דאיגא אמילתא טובא
*Hava da'iga a'milsa tuva*, she was very anxious about this for reason
for, you know, good reasons within the especially if you believe in
this. ההוא יומא *Hahu yoma*, that day that she was getting getting
married, שקלתא למכבנתא דצבתא *shakalta l'machvanta d'tzavta*, she took her like hair
pin, דצתה בכותא *datzta b'kusa*, and she stuck it into like a
hole in the wall to just for you know it's like to
store it there for a little while. איסטרמי *Istarmi*, and it just
by chance happened, יתיב yasiv בעיניה דחיויא *yasiv b'eineih d'chivya*, that it
stuck into the eye of a snake that was waiting there in
the wall. לצפרא *L'tzapra*, the next morning כי שקלה לה *ki shakla
lah*, when she took the hair pin out of the hole in
the wall, הוה קא סריך ואתי חיויא בתרה *hava ka sarich v'asi
chivya basrah*, she dragged the snake out with it. So she saw
that she was saved from this. אמר לה אבוה *Amar lah avuha*,
her father said to her, מאי עבדת *mai avadat*, what did you
do that saved you from this? Ah, you know like what what
did you do that would explain why why this happened that that
you were saved? אמרה ליה amra lei *Amrah lei*, she said to
him, בפניא *b'fanya*, last night אתא עניא *asa anya*, a poor person
came, קרא בבבא *kara b'vava*, was calling out at the door for
for some food, והוו טרידי כולי עלמא *v'havu tridi kulei alma*, everybody
was preoccupied, it was the like they were getting ready for the
wedding בסעודתא *bi'se'udata*, in the meal, וליכא דשמעיה *v'leika d'shamyeih*, and nobody
heard him. קאימנא *Kaimna*, so I got up, שקלתא לריסתנאי *shakalta l'ristana'ei*,
I took my either it means either this means my food or
my portion דיהבתו לי *d'yahavtu li*, that was given to me, יהבתיה
ניהליה *yahavtih nihaleih*, and I gave it to him. אמר לה *Amar
lah*, he said to her, מצוה עבדת *mitzvah avadat*, oh, you did
a מצוה *mitzvah* and that explains why you were saved. נפק רבי
עקיבא ודרש *Nafak Rabbi Akiva v'darash*, so רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* went
out and explicated and expounded: וצדקה תציל ממות *u'tzedakah tatzil mi'mavet*, צדקה
*tzedakah* saves from death. ולא ממיתה משונה *v'lo mimisah meshunah*, not just
from a painful death, אלא ממיתה עצמה *ela mimisah atzmah*, for actual
preordained death it will save you. ומדרב נחמן בר יצחק נמי אין
מזל לישראל *umiderav Nachman bar Yitzchak nami ein mazal l'Yisrael*, and you
even see that from רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*.
דאימיה דרב נחמן בר יצחק *D'imeih d'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, for the
mother of רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, אמרו לה
כלדאי Kaldayei *amru lah kalda'ei* the mother of רב נחמן בר יצחק
the כלדאי Kaldayei. said to her ברך גנבא הוי berach ganva havei
your son will be a thief. לא שבקתיה גלויי רישיה lo shavktei
giluyei reishei so what did she do? לא שבקתיה גלויי רישיה lo
shavktei giluyei reishei she did not allow him at at any times
to have an uncovered head, right? Because in the time of the
גמרא Gemara they didn't cover their head, but presumably they did understand
that covering the head was a sign of humility, so and a
sign of being aware that God was above you, so she was
extremely careful about this cause she knew what the כלדאי Caldai, had
said. אמרה ליה
and she said to him כסי רישיך כי היכי דתהוי לך אימתא
דשמיא kasei reisheich ki heichi d'teihavei lach eimata d'Shemaya cover your head
so there'll be the fear of heaven on you, again one of
the key גמרות Gemaros that leads to our practice of the men's
practice of covering their of covering their head. ובעי רחמי u'ba'ei rachamei
and also you should always pray for God's help to face up
to the challenges because, you know, because she knew what the כלדאי
had said and what his and what his nature was. לא הוה
ידע אמאי קאמרה ליה lo hava yada amai kamra lei she didn't
know why why she was saying this to him, apparently he never
was told about this statement of the
כלדאי. יומא חד yoma chad one day יתיב he was sitting קא
גרס תותי דיקלא ka garses tutei dikla he was learning underneath a
palm tree, not his own palm tree.
נפל גלימיה מעילויה nafal glimei mei'ilavei his shirt, his like his cloak
fell from over him, you know, he had his like head covered
presumably it wasn't just a כיפה, kippa, it's like you know his
cloak was all the way over him so it also sort of
kept his eyes focused like down, not looking all around, but its
his cloak fell off מעילויה רישיה me'ilavei reishei from his head. דלי
עיניה dali einei he lifted up his eyes חזא לדיקלא chaza l'dikla
he saw this gorgeous palm tree. אלמיה יצריה almei yitzrei his יצר
הרע yetzer hara got the better of him. סליק פסקיה לקיבורא בשיניה
salik paskei l'kibura b'shinei he went up to the palm tree and
took took a bunch of dates with his bit it off with
his teeth. He was so overwhelmed with his passion for this and
unable to control it even though it wasn't his his own. Now
what's very nice by the way about the last גמרא Gemara. is
the last גמרא Gemara, the same you know speaks about how you
know how it's not just in the metaphysical way that you can
be saved from this, but how actually you know how education and
training yourself can also you know work against your natural inclinations. So
if you just abstract and this and break the whole astrology part,
basically like
different people are born with different types of inclinations, but it doesn't
determine who you'll be like the whole story about the bloodshedder, and
and also it can be you know it can be redirected or
you know it can be controlled based on education and working on
yourself and so on. That's certainly some of the themes, but obviously
this גמרא Gemara is very disturbing because of because who in this
גמרא, Gemara how many opinions in this גמרא did not believe in
astrology? They all did! They all did, there wasn't one. At the
most they said it didn't apply to ישראל Yisrael and even those
who said it didn't apply to ישראל basically were saying it pretty
much it does have influence but not as determinant and can somehow
be overridden. Okay, so I have here for you, yeah I didn't
hand this out but whatever, an excerpt from רמב"ם's Rambam's letter on
astrology. I don't know if people are aware of it. Wait, let
me finish. רמב"ם's Rambam's letter on astrology and we don't have so
much time but I will just read to you that he says
you know the beginning all says obviously this has all been proven
to be a lie,
etcetera, etcetera. Anybody who looks at science knows that this is complete
foolishness. If you want to look at the second paragraph on the
end, it says the position of the astrologers is given lie by
reason, for correct reasoning has already refuted by means of lucid proofs
all the follies that they have maintained. It's also regarded as a
falsehood by us because of religious tradition, actually from a תורה Torah
perspective, for if the matter stood thus of what utility would the
תורה Torah and the commandments and the תלמוד Talmud be to a
particular individual if all determined? Now of course you could say a
lot, you know you could still have בחירה חופשית bechira chofshis on
certain things, but anyway רמב"ם Rambam says it really goes against the
grain of the Jewish tradition to think that all these things are
influenced by the stars. Now the last paragraph he says, the summary
of the matter is that our mind cannot grasp how the decrees
of the Holy One work upon human beings in this world, the
world to come, you know and the idea of what influences us
in this world. We have all said about this from the beginning
is the entire position of the star-gazers is regarded as falsehood by
all men of science. Now, how about our גמרא? I know that
you may search and find things of some individual sages in the
תלמוד Talmud and מדרשים Midrashim whose word appears to maintain that at
a moments of a man's birth the stars will cause such and
such to happen to him. It seems like the Rabbis believed in
this. Do not regard this as difficulty. Don't let that bother you,
for it is not fitting for man to abandon the prevailing law
and raise once again the counter-arguments and follies, meaning we've already established
that this is nonsense. So don't get worried, oh no, actually that's
not what he's saying. He was actually saying is, he's saying like
that was all like שקלא וטריא, shakla v'tarya, that was all like
at a stage of discussion, but it wasn't really like the conclusion
of the גמרא. It certainly seems like it was. Similarly, it's not
proper to abandon matters of reason that have all I think that's
what he means it could be explained that way. Or maybe it
just means let's not re-debate things we've already proven. Similarly, it's not
proper to abandon matters of reason that have already been
verified by proofs, shake them loose, and depend on the words of
a single one of the sages who possibly the matter was in
maybe there was one of the Rabbis who didn't understand this, or
there may be an allusion in these words, either he didn't mean
it literally, or maybe they've been said with a view to the
times and the business before them, which maybe means like maybe they
didn't believe in it but maybe they were talking... to the people
who did believe in it. And then he goes on. So basically
what the רמב״ם Rambam says is, yeah, okay, so the rabbis believed
it, but he tries to very much marginalize it and say maybe
it was only one rabbi, maybe they, you know, they didn't really
believe it, they didn't really mean it, they were only saying it
because that's what the people of the time believed and maybe to
address them. Anyway, it's interesting, it's similar to what the רמב״ם Rambam
does when he says, when he says, you know, there won't be
a miraculous time at the time of משיח. Mashiach. So he says,
אמרו חכמים אין בין העולם הזה לימות המשיח אלא שעבוד מלכויות בלבד.
Amru Chachamim, Ein bein olam hazeh limot hamashiach ela shibud malchuyot bilvad.
The sages say the only difference between now and messianic times is
that we won't be under the subjugation of foreign kingdoms. The sages
in the plural. It happens to be one one person, שמואל, who
says that, but he's made it that everybody else is the minority
view, this is the majority view. So here too, he tries to
somehow, you know, bracket this whole גמרא, but clearly it seems that
the, at least every rabbi here really did believe in it. תוספות,
Tosafot, by the way, does point out, if you just look at
תוספות, Tosafot, somebody asked, isn't it עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? So תוספות
Tosafot says, כלדאי, if you look at that תוספות, Tosafot, he says...
he
says, בכולה סוגיא משמע דהיינו חוזים בכוכבים. bechula sugya mashma dehainu chozim
bakochavim. That's astrologers. ולא כמו שפירש רש״י בפרק פסחים מניין שאין שואלים
בכלדיים שנאמר תמים תהיה ופירש דהיינו אוב. Velo kimo shepeirash Rashi beperek
Pesachim minayin she’ein shoalin bechaldayim shene’emar tamim tihiyeh upeirash dehainu ov. Which
is אוב, ov, which is a necromancer. ועוד קשיא דבהדיא כתיב אל
תפנו אל האובות. Ve’od kasha deheidiya ktiv al tifnu el ha’ovot. Okay,
so תוספות Tosafot says it's not like the real heavy stuff that's
forbidden
about necromancy and so on. But still, even within תוספות, Tosafot, fine,
but it's still prohibited by the, by תמים תהיה עם ה׳ אלקיך,
tamim tihiyeh im Hashem Elokecha, that you should not, you should be,
have full faith in God and not worry about this stuff. But,
you know, that becomes a question at what stage is this even
transgressing biblical prohibitions. Yes.
But he seems even according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, and you know,
his dismissal of astrology, he still believe that God controls the world
through the stars, didn't he? That like, you know... No. He did
say like although there's no like מזל but like but still God
directs everything through... I remember reading that in the רמב״ם. Rambam.
Yeah... okay, you know what, you can read the whole letter of
astrology, I'm not going to get into it.
The main thing is though but again like back to I'm still
surprised that, you know, what about like all the things like you're
a Scorpio, you're a this, how none of that came in there?
You know, and doesn't it, you know, don't we also even have
this? Like you know, you look in your מחזור... Machzor...
Yeah, about like what time the season, yeah. I don't know, I
don't know, I don't know. Okay, so let's get onto the next
small area bit. משנה. Mishnah.
What was the context of this letter by the way?
That's a good question. He was writing it to rabbis in Southern
France. So,
you know, I don't know, like if they asked him the question
about what his position is on this. It's actually a good question,
I'll have to, I'll have to check. You know, I'm sure if,
I'm sure two seconds on the internet will provide an answer to
that. Okay, מקצצין את הדלעת לפני הבהמה. mekatzin et hadla'at lifnei habehemah.
You can chop up a gourd in front of animals. Again, we're
getting to issues about feeding animals, but here the concern is not
so much about effort, although the גמרא brought it in the whole
discussion of effort, here the concern is מוקצה. muktzah. Why מוקצה? muktzah?
Because a gourd is set aside for human consumption, but presumably you'd
have to cook it. Okay, so you want to take something set
aside for human consumption, is it considered מוקצה muktzah to use it
for animal consumption? That's a really weird type of a מוקצה, muktzah,
because it's something that actually, you know, is not like unusable, it's
just something you want to use. But okay, but maybe it's you
can't use it on שבת Shabbat for yourself, but you still don't
want to be using it on שבת Shabbat. because normally you'd use
it for your animal. But no, that's okay, that's a נבלה לפני
הכלבים neveilah lifnei haklavim and you could also cut up a carcass,
an animal carcass in front of dogs, even if it died on
שבת. Shabbat So when שבת Shabbat began, it was not fit for
dogs and it was set aside for human consumption. That's not a
problem. The basic principle here is מוקצה לאדם לא הוי מוקצה לבהמה.
muktzah leadam lo havei muktzah lebehemah. Okay, if it's מוקצה muktzah for
man, a person, it's not מוקצה muktzah for animals.
Or לכלבים leclavim
is normally the phrase. רבי יהודה אומר אם לא היתה נבלה מערב
שבת אסורה. Rabbi Yehuda omer im lo hayta neveilah me’erev Shabbat asura.
No, if it hadn't died from before שבת Shabbat. it's forbidden, לפי
שאינו מן המוכן. lefi she’eino min hamuchan. It is not set aside.
So this is the basic debate that גמרא frames as, although here
it's a very local one and maybe it has to do with
a specific aspect of מוקצה, muktzah, but understands it רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
not, and frames it that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't believe in
מוקצה muktzah and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does believe in מוקצה, muktzah,
although here again it's, you know, it's not as absolute. So let's
just get started with that in the גמרא. אתמר, Itmar, it was
said, אמר עולא הלכה כרבי יהודה. amar Ulla halacha keRabbi Yehuda. We
rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, I don't know why that, sorry.
We rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, I'll read the parentheses, שמואל
אמר הלכה כרבי שמעון. veShmuel amar halacha keRabbi Shimon. We rule like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ואף רבא סבר לה כרבי יהודה. Ve'af Rava
savar lah keRabbi Yehuda. And רבא Rava holds we rule like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. מדיקרקי דזוזי, Midikarki dezuzi, from
because these like covers, these these, what were they called, these things
that you put, these covers on that you put on, tarps? Right,
tarps, tarps that you put over things on the boats דרבא אסר
ושמואל שרי. deRava asar veShmuel shari. רבא Rava said it's forbidden, שמואל
said it's permissible. So somehow that means he rules like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, he has a broader category of מוקצה. muktzah. Who knows
what the issue was by those tarps. ואף לוי סבר לה כרבי
יהודה. Ve'af Levi savar lah keRabbi Yehuda. And לוי Levi holds we
rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. כי הא דלוי כד הוי מייתי
טרפתא לקמיה ביומא טבא. Ki ha deLevi kavei maisi treifta lekamei beyoma
tava.
When לוי Levi was, somebody would ask an animal they שחט shecht
on יום טוב Yom Tov and they'd ask לוי Levi to look
at it to see if it was a טרפה treifah and because
it was יום טוב, Yom Tov, you could שחט shecht the animal.
לא הוי חזי לה, Lo havi chazei lah, he wouldn't be, he
wouldn't be prepared to look at the animal, אלא כי יתיב אקיקלתא,
ela ki yativ akiklotei, until he was sitting by a dump. Great
place to sit for your פסק. ואמר דילמא לא מיכשרה, Ve'amar, dilma
lo miskashra, maybe it won't be kosher, I'll say it's טרפה, treifah,
ואפילו לכלבים לא חזי. ve'afilu leclavim lo chazi.
Now this is exactly the case of the משנה, Mishnah, an animal
that died on שבת. Shabbos, On יום טוב, Yom Tov, meaning basically
on יום טוב Yom Tov it only became fit for dogs. It
was שחט shachted but it was טריפה. treif. And he says then
I won't allow you to feed it even to your dogs because
that's exactly the case of the משנה, mishna, an animal that was
fit for humans consumption or we thought it was, it died on
שבת, here it was שחט shachted on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you cannot eat you cannot even
feed it to the dogs. It's מוקצה. muktsa. So we'd have to
just leave it there at the dump. Okay, ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי
שמעון. v'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. We rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow, but again it's
quite fascinating that the גמרא, whatever they said in the thing, that
the גמרא assumes that there's this like absolute debate, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda holds of מוקצה, muktsa, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not. In
our משנה, mishna, it's specifically a local question of something that was
set aside for human food and now you want to use it
for animal food. And at least the case of שמואל and the
טריפה treifa was that example, but the גמרא will see abstracts it
to see as much bigger debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so we will wrap all of that up tomorrow.